Stanford
University was talking about what
happens during or from beginning from
before a measurement to after a
measurement they were talking about what
happens to the evolution of an isolated
black hole left to itself between the
time that it was prepared and the time
it was measured okay uh nevertheless I
could answer the question is is
entanglement
inevitably
irreversible if two things which are not
entangled come together interact with
each other do whatever they do and
become entangled is it irreversible not
necessarily anything that can
happen the opposite can happen and now
we're not talking about an external
apparatus measuring a system we're s
simply talking for example about two
spins two spins interact with each other
come together go off and they're
entangled what happens is it possible to
disentangle them by for example
reflecting them letting them come
together and interact again can they
become disentangled yes yes there's no
rule that says entanglement is uh is
irreversible on the other hand if an
entanglement happens and you take one of
the electrons off and throw it away
then the other one is stuck there left
being entangled with a thing that just
is um not going to come
back not going to come back unless of
course somebody out there throw reflects
it back in so yeah entanglement is re is
reversible but as far as you're
concerned the measurements that you do
are
irreversible that's a very peculiar
situation and you have to think about it
to understand what it means uh we're
going to move we're going to move off
the question of these very
simple systems spins sometimes called
cubits uh tonight at some point but I
want to just uh uh go over just very
briefly I think I probably discussed
this in class last time but nevertheless
it's so important that I'm that uh that
I want
to um hammer on it first of all there
was a notion of a density Matrix if we
have two systems Alice's system and Bob
system and Alice is and Bob system are
far away from each other so that Alice
doesn't get to do any experiments on Bob
system Bob doesn't get to do any
experiments on alysis system but they're
entangled either they are or they are
not entangled they may be entangled is
there a description that Alice by
herself uses to describe just just her
subsystem the answer is yes and the
working description of her subsystem is
called the density Matrix so let me just
review that very very
quickly and uh go back over some
Concepts if the wave function of the
Alice Bob system the combined
system of Alice's subsystem and Bob's if
the wave function
is called s of a and b b for Bob a for
Alice then Alice's Alice's density
Matrix Alice's density Matrix is defined
to be
siar the complex conjugate of the wave
function all right now let's say row
it's row called the density matrix it's
indicated by
row it has subscripts a and a prime
because it's a matrix
but it doesn't have anything to do with
Bob so it's purely a matrix with respect
to Alice's variables let's indicate that
by calling this Alice's density
Matrix and it's
given by SAR of
a a prime B I always get confused yeah a
prime s of
ab summed over
Bob's
variables it doesn't depend on Bob's
variables because they've been summed
over when you sum over something it no
longer depends on that set of variables
so this is only a function of Alice's
variables and it contains all
possible all possible
um statistical information that Alice
can ever know
about her half of the system
unless Bob comes and interacts with her
system of course if Bob comes from
wherever he is and gives her system a
shot of some sort that will change her
density Matrix but as long as Bob stays
away from her system Bob's in paloalto
Alice is on Alpha centuri as long as Bob
does not interact directly with her
system her density Matrix doesn't change
no matter what what Bob does let me give
a little proof of
that uh let's take Bob's sub subsystem
to not be so narrow as just to be the
little spin that he's carrying around
and also Alice's let's
imagine that Alice's subsystem consists
of everything in Alice's neighborhood
everything that she can have any contact
with and everything in Bob system is uh
everything everything in Bob's
neighborhood maybe even including Bob
and now Bob is going to do something
he's going to do something interact of
course he can only interact direct
interact May mean he may turn on in a
magnetic field he may do all sorts of
things uh to change the evolution of his
subsystem he's going to make a subsystem
evolve in some
way what are the way
which Bob can cause his subsystem to
evolve many many ways but whatever they
are they are always governed by unitary
matrices let's come over here and forget
Alice for a minute and ask what Bob can
do to his subsystem he has a wave
function let's leave Alis out of the
picture Al
together just let's suppose that Bob has
a wave function and he's going to
manipulate his system
somehow he's going to manipulate the
system somehow and send it to a new wave
function the rule is the new wave
function of his subsystem must be
related to the old wave function by a
unitary operator unitary operators are
the things which govern time Evolution
go back remember about time Evolution
unitary operators and that means that s
of B becomes replaced by some over B
some unitary Matrix
BB
Prime s of B
Prime in terms of wave functions and
matrices this is the description of what
happens to Bob's Matrix sorry Bob's
column Vector this is basically Bob's
column Vector describing his half of the
world or his
system and to find out what happens to
it no matter what he does even if he
doesn't do anything uh but let's suppose
he does something if he does something
it generates a unitary evolution of his
wave function now how do we describe the
same thing in the composite language in
the composite
language if the wave function is s of A
and B Alice's and Bob's variable what
happens to it when Bob manipulates his
half of the world
exactly the same thing with Alice's
variables being just Spectators just
being passive Spectators so s of A and B
just becomes s of whoops let's put in
there b Prime this is sum of B
Prime this is a function of B and you
sum over B
Prime okay that's again a sum of a b
Prime of U of B and B
Prime s of A and B prime a just passed
through Alice knew nothing whatever
about uh about this whole process her
subsystem was not in any way influenced
her her um index or her part of the wave
function her half of the dependence of
the wave function was uninfluenced by
Bob's
manipulation so let's go back and take
the manipulated wave function is the
manipulated wave
function let's call it
s uh manipulated the manipulated wave
function of b and a of A and
B that's this it's been modified by the
action of
Bob's unitary
operator okay now let's recalculate
let's
recalculate
Alice's density
Matrix after all Alice's density Matrix
contains all information that she can
ever know about her half of the world
and so let's see what happened to it
well we first of all have to take the
manipulated size
star we we still have some over B but
now we take the manipulated size star oh
we haven't written size star sorry about
that we have to write size
star manipulated of and we want to know
about it with index a prime and
B A Prime and B and that we get just by
complex conjugating this tells us how
side changes let's just work out the
complex conjugate that's the complex
conjugate
of a prime
where is it A and B
Prime this is a this is a prime and B
just a prime and B but here since B
Prime is a summation variable we do not
want to write B Prime here B Prime was
the summation variable used over here
let's just invent another one called
bble
Prime we're going to be that's going to
be a summation variable in a moment and
U complex
conjugate of
uh B and B
Prime yeah U complex conjugate and of
course there's a sum over B Prime
here and the only reason I called it B
Prime instead of B Prime was so as not
to confuse it with B Prime here's one
sum and here's a separate
sum right now here's something what do
we know about unitary operators unitary
operators
our operators that if we
interchange B if we interchange the two
indices and complex conjugate what
happens that's called it's called the
inverse operator or the Herm Mission
conjugate for a unit in general it's
called the hermiss
conjugate specifically for a unary it
becomes the inverse
operator let's just call it the
conjugate if
I un complex conjugate and interchange
these two sorry B Prime B Prime B then
this becomes Herm Mission
conjugate all right so this is the usual
story if operators operate to the right
on K vectors the corresponding action on
bra vectors is given by the um by the
her mission conjugate all right so now
all we have to do is plug this in we
plug this in for the left for the for
the manipulated SI star that's summation
over b b
Prime uh
SAR of a prime and B
Prime Times U
Dagger of BP Prime and B
that's a nuisance too many indices for
me to be comfortable in the Blackboard
but I think this is worth doing now what
about SII SII is the other half that
comes into the uh density Matrix and
that's U BB
Prime s of
what s of A and B Prime
complicated little
mess
oh when what are we summing
over we're summing over all the B's
basically yeah we're summing over this B
over here let's put a b summation here
we were summing over B Prime to get the
manipulated wave the complex conjugate
but we also have to sum over B Prime
here sum over all the B's in sight each
B is a summation variable by the time
we're
finished all right but now look at what
we have it looks complicated but what is
this thing over
here well not quite yeah one is uh
essentially correct but of course what
you mean is the unit
Matrix this is the product Matrix of UD
dagger this is a unitary Matrix so UD
dagger is used inverse B Prime B BB
Prime this is just just the chronica
Delta B Prime B prime it just instructs
you to set B Prime equal to B
Prime when you do the sum when you do
one of the two sums let's say the bble
prime sum so all of this then
becomes sum over B Prime well let's see
what have we got we've we've said bble
Prime yeah we've done the sum of B
that's done no sum over B we just did it
and now we set B Prime equal to B Prime
s star of a prime B Prime s of A and B
Prime that's
it now it doesn't matter whether we call
B Prime B prime or whether we call it B
because it's a summation variable so
let's do that let's just call it B and
what do we have we have exactly I hope I
pray the original density Matrix so Bob
no matter what he does as long as what
he does is described by a unitary
Matrix Bob will have absolutely no
effect on Alice's density Matrix does
not matter whether they're entangled or
not nowhere did I specify that this was
a product
state that is what physicists call
locality the
inability of Bob to influence any
statistical prediction of
Alice's by doing a manipulation on his
own degrees of
freedom locality is not
violated this form of locality this form
of locality is not violated in any way
by the phenomenon of
entanglement that's the technical
argument okay notice that it does depend
on unitarity so and what did unitarity
do with unitarity had to do with
conservation of pro of
um of uh
distinctions what I call the minus first
law at least in its quantum mechanical
version so there a funny in an
interesting interplay funny interesting
interplay between the conservation of
Distinction on the one hand and locality
if Bob somehow had
access to changes which were not
described by unitary operators this
would not have become the unit Matrix
over here and the final density Matrix
would Alice's final density Matrix
indeed would have been
modified this is interesting the way the
whole thing holds together this is why
it's so hard to change quantum mechanics
you want to play play a little game
Let's uh let Bob let's let Bob's
Evolution not quite be unitary only
approximately unitary well then
immediately you start sending signals
faster than the speed of light how by
instantly modifying Alice's uh density
Matrix so things hold together tightly
and it's hard to change
them
um good so yes so so is it correct to
say that if bomb's
um Matrix is unitary the evolution
Matrix yeah can't do he's not really
able to touch his system he's not able
to he's not able to change
Alice Alice's system he's changed his
own system by doing something and that
doing something was described by this
unitary Matrix okay that that that's the
part that excuses me if it's if he's
doing something isn't he going to be
violating
unitarity no um for example he might be
turning a
magnet he might be turning a magnet in
such a way that it has an influence on
his
spin what does that influence it will
change the state of the spin for
example
yeah if you have a spin in a given
Direction and it's coupled to a magnetic
field and you and you turn the magnetic
field field in some way you'll typically
change the evolution of that
spin okay so Bob can do that he can um
change a magnetic field that's acting on
a certain spin the result will be to
change the way the spin evolves that
will change his own measurements of the
spin of his
spin if he does
ACT by rotating a magnetic field which
is mathematically described by some sort
of evolution doesn't matter what some
sort of evolution it's described by a
unitary operator then
uh then he does change the results of
his own
measurements for examp he he rotates the
magnetic field but he doesn't rotate his
apparatus the result is that he going to
change the probability distributions of
his own spin but he will not change any
of the probabilities of Alice's spin
okay so so are you saying quantum
mechanics is always Obe
locality morality
defined by the inability of Bob to
influence Alice's
measurements okay yeah now the question
so what's the big deal is that what
you're G to
ask I was um guessing what you were
going to ask why don't you ask it
s single particle wave function put a
photon through a beam splitter it goes
off in two different directions you
catch it at one detector faster than the
speed of light the wave function
collapses whoa whoa whoa who
what you you do what you you detect a
photon at one detector yeah the the wave
function at the other detector collapses
to zero
instantaneously I showed you what
happens the density Matrix of the other
system does not change period
really average measurements don't
change what what what
happen I know I know I know people look
I'm doing my absolute best to tell it to
you as it really is and to cut through
the crap that's out
there to cut through the crap that's out
there because there is a huge amount of
of there is a pile a mile high and we
somehow want to cut through that this is
the mathematics of cutting through it
now nevertheless there were some pretty
damn smart people who are uncomfortable
about something something that they call
nonlocality I mean you know Einstein was
no jerk he was pretty
smart and uh they didn't call him
Einstein for nothing that's my favorite
joke
John Bell was pretty smart they didn't
call him Einstein
though yeah so there's something going
on there's something going on yeah go
ahead this goes back to
or I want to get I'm reviewing last week
so uh make it quick to me this this is
real clear I think um and that is the
your idea of loc locality means that the
the state
don't affect each other words there's
there's two things the
density yeah and and it seems that in uh
the confusing part of quantum mechanics
is that those two different things get
mixed up somehow is that accurate
or no it's
fuzzy but it's
true that it up a
lot so I will try to I will try to tell
you as I understand
it what
the concrete operational facts are right
so I I told you last time I was I was a
little bit um tired last time and I'm
not sure I was completely clear so I
going to go over it again because it's
very very
interesting uh and it really is at the
heart of all of the confusions about
confusions I mean I must say including
my own internal confusions about uh
quantum mechanics when I first learned
about her Einstein Rosen podowski that
was the discovery well I don't know if
it was I don't know if it was a
discovery I think maybe schinger said
some things about
entanglement but it was Einstein Rosen
and Podolski who really called attention
to how peculiar it was basically what
they said is we have a very funny
situation here where although we can
know everything that can possibly be
known about a composite system we know
nothing at all about its constituents
that's crazy that violates my sense of
reality that violates my sense of uh of
what it means to know what a system is
doing violates all sorts of things I
remember when I first heard about it it
was actually before John Bell sometime
in the 60s when I was a student no I
wasn't a student I was a young assistant
professor and I started to think about
it and I thought about it a lot and
tried to figure out what it means um I
was sort of inclined to try to think
about it in terms of simulating quantum
mechanics and I still am what are the
limits if if if quantum mechanics is so
very strange and so very different than
classical physics does it mean that you
can't fool somebody into thinking a
system is quantum mechanical if all you
have your resources are entirely
classical and the answer is yes and no
so I know I talked about this last time
but it really is at the center of things
so let's go back over it quick quick as
I can we're going to build ourselves a
Quantum simulator I think somebody built
one on the uh on the site I came across
it about an hour ago who who's that yeah
does does it work uh not well it it
doesn't actually simulate yet not yet
but is that picture is that picture your
picture there was a picture of Einstein
and Heisenberg and Einstein says I don't
like this and Heisenberg said what uh
Einstein says I I think I'm not going to
like this yeah right oh
yes right I think that captures it why
go on but okay let's let's talk about
the nature of quantum simulators all
right first of all I just want to
simulate a single spin I think I told
you how to do it but let's uh write down
the steps we have a computer
screen there's our computer screen on
the screen we have a picture of a
detector not a detector an apparatus and
the apparatus can be oriented in any
direction in three-dimensional space we
need to do some three-dimensional
graphics
here and it has a window and the window
shows one of
three possible States one is called
blank B that's the uh that's the
detector or the apparatus before it's uh
interacted with anything so it can be b
or it can be plus or minus
one B is not important it's just uh to
say before the detector interacts with
anything there's a button over here
called
M and um the operator of the system of
the computer game basically all he ever
gets to do is press M and then look at
the result of the an m stands for
measure it performs a measurement now
over here connected to the computer by
wires uh by
cables uh connected to the screen by
cables is a computer and the computer
stores information in its memory and the
basic information that it stores is two
complex numbers Alpha up and Alpha down
those are supposed to be the components
of the wave function of the spin I
didn't say yet that there was a spin
here but that's what we're that's what
we're talking about Alpha up and Alpha
down the
computer only can generate Alphas which
satisfy Alpha star Alpha up plus Alpha
star Alpha down is equal to
one whenever whenever it generates them
it uh and it can do something else can
do two other
things it can update the alphas by
solving the schinger equation for them
there's some hamiltonian for example it
could be that the spins are in a the
spin is in a in an imaginary magnetic
field in which case the alphas would
change with time the computer knows how
to do that it knows how to solve
Schrodinger's equation computers can
solve Schrodinger's equation beautifully
and it updates these as a function of
time updates them according to the rules
of quantum mechanics one other thing the
cables are instantaneous they convey
information
instantly all right so we'll have one
more element the other element will be a
random number generator let me just say
some words about random number
generators random number generators
sounds like we're introducing quantum
mechanics no we don't need quantum
mechanics
uh you can simulate to a very very high
degree of
confidence Rand a sequence of random
numbers or random number generator
purely out of classical uh classical
considerations you know how to do it you
take the digits of pi or
whatever and uh you make something that
looks would fool anybody including a
sophisticated mathematician into
believing uh that you were generating a
set of random numbers so there's a
random number generator in the computer
all right the operator starts by
initializing the system and and
initializing the
system uh simply means starting out some
orientation for the detector for the
apparatus doesn't matter what and
setting the alphas to some initial
values uh he can plug in what he wants
to the initial values to be or the
computer just sets them according to
whatever rule it likes the then the
system runs for a period of time an
indeterminant period of time updating
the alphas
until the operator
decides to press m a certain amount of
time is elapsed the operator decides how
much time and presses M at that point
the random number generator generates a
plus one or a minus one but with
probability Alpha star Alpha up that
it's plus one sorry Alpha up Alpha up
star that it's plus one or else Alpha
star Alpha down that it's minus one
remember the sum of these two alpha star
Alphas add up to one so with with armed
with the random number generator the
computer sends a signal with a
probability of the appropriate
probability to the detector and the
detector detects or
registers what the computer sent it okay
that's one measurement now as soon as
that happens the computer
reinitializes the alphas how does it
reinitialize the alphas if the detector
detected plus
one then it sends back a message it
doesn't really need to send back a
message after all this message got from
here to here all right so the computer
over here knows whether it got plus one
or minus one if the detector saw + one
then it sets Alpha U Back to one and
sends Alpha D to
zero in other words it does what we call
collapsing the wave function according
to
the result or according to the outcome
of the measurement it
reinitializes the Alphas
so whatever was
measured you start with probability one
for the outcome and probability zero for
the what shall we call it the anti-
outcome and then it runs again solves a
shinger equation does it again the
operator makes a ramp makes whatever
decision he likes I mean what makes him
decide to pressure to press M he's an
experimental physicist what makes
experimental physicists do what they do
I don't really know but uh but he does
what experimental physicists do now and
then he presses M and does the whole
operation over again oh sorry before he
does he may decide to rotate the
apparatus now the computer in here knows
what the orientation of the apparatus is
so when it
calculates it not only Cal calculates
the updated Alphas but it also
calculates the probabilities for the
rotated detector to detect whatever it's
going to detect that's all algebra and a
little bit of uh that's that's purely
algebra the computer makes the kind of
calculations that you did presumably did
makes the kind of calculations to
calculate what the probability would be
that if the detector was rotated in some
arbitrary Direction then uh then what's
the probability that it will get up or
down now who is it that decides to
rotate the computer well it's the
operator again the experimentalist the
experimentalist not only can press M but
he can also reorient the detector
anytime he
wants this is about as much as an
experimental physicist can do with that
spin rotate the apparatus
measure rotate the apparatus again
measure right and what's the result of
the outcome of this the outcome of this
is
indistinguishable from what the
experimental physicist examining the
spin would see so we've simulated
quantum
mechanics all right now we want to know
whether we can simulate quantum
mechanics of two
spins one on Alice's side of the world
over here and one on Bob's side of the
world
yeah um I don't understand the purpose
of the button m in our in our uh in
other
words when when he decides to push it
some amount of time is involved yeah has
that has that affected anything going on
in the computer yeah the computer has
been updating all this time right but
when we talked about our basic model of
how spin Works time did not come into it
at all we we did talk about
hamiltonians we talked about
hamiltonians and how hamiltonians update
the state of a system you're right we
didn't discuss how a uh we didn't
discuss much about hamiltonians for
spins yes we did yes we did I believe I
described a spin and a magnetic field
and how the average spin
processes we did but if we didn't have
the magnetic field because that's how we
started out talking about all this stuff
right then then time is not a should not
be a factor okay I understand thank you
m right now there's no real magnetic
field there's just an imaginary magnetic
field that the computer knows about and
where does that come into it it comes
into the solution the the nature of the
exact shinger equation
okay now we do this over here and
precisely the same thing over here
except instead of Alphas we have betas
beta stands for
Bob exactly the same setup replicated
twice Bob does his measurement Alice
does her measurements they're perfectly
happy each one says I have a spin it's
quantum mechanical they don't talk to
each other and each one says my spin is
in a state
the language that we would describe this
by Quantum mechanically is they have
simulated a product State a product
state in which Bob's sorry Alice's wave
function is this and Bob's wave function
is this and the combined system is in a
product State supposing now we want to
simulate a any state a more complete
description that includes entangled
States well we can do it this way let's
start with a way that's sort of
guaranteed to
work we take the computer and we put it
in the middle a single
computer we can think of a single
computer if we like as a pair of
computers connected by wires but just by
the fact that they're communicating with
each other and interacting with each
other really makes them a single
computer and in that single computer we
now store four complex numbers the four
complex numbers that we store in there
are
Alpha up up Alpha up down Alpha down up
Alpha down
down these complex numbers here are not
necessarily products in fact let's
assume they're not products in other
words that this is not a product State
let's assume it's a highly entangled
State even a highly entangled state is
described by four complex numbers like
this that's what's in the
computer and what does a computer do
with it
it evolves the Schrodinger equation
first of all we initialize same deal we
initialize we start with some
Alphas the
alphas are allowed to run according to
whatever Schrodinger equation describes
them and at the end either Bob or Alice
or
both without knowing what the other one
is doing press or as the case may be
don't press their me measurement buttons
once the measurement button has been
pressed an instantaneous signal goes
back to the computer the computer grinds
out its random number generator and
whichever side was measured sends a
signal to the detector with appropriate
probability either plus one or minus one
and then reinitializes
itself reinitializes itself in a way
that doesn't touch for example if Alice
does the
experiment
then it doesn't touch Bob's end of
things if Bob does the experiment the
computer reinitializes his half of the
wave function which is another way of
saying it throws away the piece that you
didn't measure throws away the pieces
you didn't measure and renormalizes the
wave function so that the total
probability is
one exactly the same thing there's no no
real difference with a single system you
can simulate it and you can simulate it
in a way which would describe all the
possible things that Alice and Bob could
measure in whether or not the system was
um was entangled okay where is where do
we get in trouble we get in trouble if
after
initializing we try to separate the
computers and break the
wires for example here's what we might
do get given these Alphas we might put
them into both
computers take the set of Alphas that we
generated put this one into this
computer this one into this computer now
since the computers are not going to
talk to each other they have to have
separate random number
generators the random number generators
will not talk to each other each one
contains the Full entangled
State and then we go through the same
operation what's going to happen happen
the computer is simply going to
forget for example for an highly
entangled State let's say the entangled
state is the singlet
State then the right answer would be
that if Bob and Alice both
measure they should get opposite values
for any spin if they measure the X
component of spin they should get
opposite values if they measure y
components of spin they should get
opposite values but if when we separate
them they have separate random number
generators and the random number
generators don't talk to each other then
guess what's going to happen there's
going to be no correlation of any kind
between what Bob measures and what Alice
measures no Bob May measure plus and
Alice may also measure plus because
their random number generators are not
connected to each other and so even
though both computers may know about the
full of the system if the random number
generators don't talk to each other
then the results of the
experiments will not contain the
correlation the correlation that Bob and
Alice could later come together and
Report Bob would say my first
experiments are a plus if things were
working right then alysis should say my
first experiments are a minus and so
forth and so on that c corelation will
not be there once you try to separate
the computers are the random numbers
correlated if you don't separate the
computers wa you can have you can have
uh you can have a single random number
generator that sends out signals to both
computers if it sends out a signal plus
one to this computer it sends out a
signal minus one to that
computer so all you need is a single
random number generator but it has to be
able to talk to both
computers all right so there's got to be
wires in the world there's got to be
wires in the world connecting this side
and this side if for no other reason
then they can both connect to the same
random number generator you you've got
four Alphas there but it sounds like you
just described that the alphas are
independent now you've got to think
about it yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
well that's that's sort of right once
you've separated them
then what happens next after some
measurements are made doesn't preserve
the relationship between them they
become disconnected from each
other yeah so think about it a little
bit I mean even better try to simulate
it this is this I've never tried but I
don't think it should be that hard if
you can do a little bit of computer
programming I've I've simulated much
harder things than that when uh when my
son was a little kid
we had this thing called basic anybody
remember basic and he and I designed a
basketball game and it had friction and
it had uh much harder than this so that
was my last experience ever programming
anything have a quick uh scenario and I
think you will learn a lot by trying to
simulate this okay you have a detector
called a cell phone and I get a signal
from Alice or Bob about the some random
event it could be a spin let's suppose
we're we're will you please speak
concretely we get a signal from Bob of
some random event what does it mean okay
can you please be exact I will be very
precise very exact I'm getting two text
messages one from a one from B okay and
they can have a value of one or a zero
each of them okay and I I get a million
of these things and I noticed
distribution that the a signal is about
a 50% chance of being yes one or zero
same with the be signal okay it could be
from a spin yes yes okay go ahead now I
look at the correlation it turns out
that whether it's a or b the other one
is the same in other words it's
correlated a correlation of one that's
in the real world of entangled States
right now this could be we don't know
where it's coming from I'm just getting
information so so I get an information
so a comes through I don't look at it B
comes through I know it's a 50/50 chance
I don't look at it but as soon as I look
at a I know what B is so the wave
function completely changes now the the
example I'm using is not a state I'm
just Bob and Alice or sexing twins one's
a boy once a girl you got to hurry up
because I got to get on to particles so
there is nothing magical about that
there is nothing weird about that if
it's correlated like that it's very
probable they're identical twins instead
of fraternal twins
so what am I missing what is weird about
that if you don't find it weird
good what's weird is that you can't
simulate it
classically without having
a uh Central processor connected by
wires that's what's weird about it so so
don't don't those wires that connect the
two distant computers represent
non-locality oh okay now we ask all
right those wires are there for goodness
sake surely Bob can send a message
through the wires to Alice that takes no
time at all because they're
instantaneous
yeah true enough If This Were a real
computer setup but if Bob is restricted
to only do the things which quantum
mechanics allows him to
do if he is restricted by the rules of
quantum mechanics
then we find out amazingly that Bob can
never send a message through the wires
that violates
locality why because all Bob can do is
manipulate his own system with unitary
operators
and so that's what's Curious here um
does that mean that the world is filled
up with wires that we can't see I don't
think that's the message I think the
right message but of course here you can
hear with there's room for debate what
the right message of all of this
is um the message I take away from it is
basically quantum mechanics cannot be
simulated by a classical system the
logic is too different the structures of
the two theories are too too
different and I don't take away the
message that the world is full of wires
that if only we could access them we
could send messages back and forth other
people
do uh but I think at least if we know
how to do quantum mechanics we'll agree
on the facts we may disagree on
basically whether there are or are not
wires there are there really wires there
or are there really not wires there well
perhaps the culprit is the word
really but uh but this is this is oh oh
there is one other element to it which
is quite
interesting um we've made an
assumption that
Bob and Alice get to kind of randomly
make decisions about when to uh press
the button about what orientations about
what to decide to measure Bob sits here
and
says okay
northwest southeast or whatever makes
these random decisions according uh to
the principle of Free Will so to
speak that's fine as long as Alice and
Bob are outside the system and not part
of it we don't need to ask uh the
question of Consciousness and the
question of free will will'll just admit
that Alice and Bob can make random
decisions about when to went to measure
various things it's obviously a pretty
good
approximation but once we take Alice and
Bob and put them into the system so that
they are governed by the laws of physics
then things get a little bit touchy what
do we mean by saying that Alice can
decide to do this or Bob can decide to
do that and that I think is where the
possible loopholes in all of this can
come from that
uh now I I don't want to get too deep
into heavy philosophical discussions of
uh of all sorts of psychological and
questions of
Consciousness I don't know the answers
that's that's it I don't know the
answers beyond what I've told
you uh I'm certain of two things about
it I am certain that there are a lot of
people who think they do know the
answers and I'm also certain that they
don't question um actually not a
question comment um if you Google for
Quantum Randy challenge you'll find a
blog entry that has the setup for this
simulation really yeah for the for the
entangled case it doesn't solve it it
says if you can here's a program yeah
your challenge is to put fill in this
blank place I see and if you can he'll
give you a million dollars hey okay
actually he won't give you a million
dollars somebody in Sweden will give you
a million
dollars yeah okay that's very
interesting okay so I'm not the first
one to well I bet I was the first one to
think about it this way but I've been
telling this people for 50 years h
no I don't know I I probably wasn't I I
think I think maybe bore thought about
it this way who knows doesn't matter um
let's uh we we we could spend the rest
of Eternity talking about spins there so
why because they really are
interesting but uh you know we want to
get to something else we want to get to
particles we want to get to more complex
systems the most complex system we've
disc discussed this two spins
four-dimensional Hilbert
space uh we've gotten about to the point
where in classical physics we got
through the first lecture the first
lecture was about these simple discrete
systems and then we rather immediately
moved on to continuous motion of things
like particles moving continuously with
an infinite and not just an infinite but
a continuously infinite range of
possibilities that's where we have to go
now now fortunately we've set so much of
the apparatus of quantum mechanics that
we can do it fairly
quickly we there's a little bit of
subtlety about replacing sums by
integrals that's about it that's about
the nature of the subtlety sums and
integrals we've expressed the general
principles of quantum
mechanics and then exhibited it in uh in
a variety of simple spin system examples
now we plunge right
in to quantum
gravity
no yes we'll plunge right in to the
problem of a single particle moving on a
one-dimensional
axis okay uh we'll take the axis to be
infinite although we if we uh that's
mostly because I don't have time to be
more
careful if we want to get anywhere we're
going to have to to
um uh be
uh slightly less mathematically
rigorous right so we have and in order
to be rigorous you really have to
contain a system in a finite volume and
so forth but we don't need to do that so
we have a line infinite line along that
infinite line one particle can exist we
won't do two particles yet one particle
can exist in one dimension
and that line is labeled by a coordinate
X let me not write down the coordinate X
but also the states of the
particle the states of the particle are
also labeled by the position of a
particle now here we are departing from
classical logic In classical Logic the
states of a particle are labeled by a
position and a
momentum uh if we were talking about the
states of a spin we would say the state
of a spin is described by all of the or
maybe at at least two of the components
of spin but we can't do that in quantum
mechanics we can't specify two
components simultaneously same in
classical mechanics specifying as you
I'm sure you know specifying the
position and the momentum is too
much uh and we'll see how that works
we'll see how that works but for the
moment let's take it as a postulate
that a complete description of the state
of a particle and you can't get any more
out uh is for example to know that it's
located at a position X and if it's
located at position X we'll describe
that by a k Vector the K Vector X that's
the state of a particle when it's
located at position
X now of course we can consider more
complicated
more complicated
States linear superpositions of these in
quantum mechanics we are always allowed
to make linear
superpositions and so the space of
states is bigger than just the space of
particles located at definite
positions let's call the General State
Sai this is the General State of a
particle doesn't mean anything now it's
just an abstract symbol and it's a
vector in some Vector space the Vector
space now has a continuously infinite
number of basis vectors now strictly
speaking that's a mathematically bad
thing but we're going to play that game
if you want to understand more deeply uh
the mathematics of quantum mechanics you
go and you learn about Hilbert Bas all
right but we're not going to do that
tonight all right so the General State
of a particle is called
sigh remember what the wave function of
a system is the wave function of a
system in a particular
basis is the projection of the state
onto the basis vectors and we call that
s of
a now we come to a particle the basis of
states are the position states and what
is the wave function the wave
function is the inner product of the
state
Vector with the igen vectors of position
and that's called s of x
that's the wave function that's the
classical not classical but that's the
standard quantum mechanical wave
function of a particle it plays the same
role as in the simple systems we've
discussed the inner product of the state
Vector with a now we can say a little
more in this context the
probability that the system whatever it
is exist property a is given by this
thing squared in fact it's given by SAR
of a s of a that's the probability that
the system is um that the outcome of an
experiment to determine whether the
system was had property a that's the
probability likewise in exact parallel
the probability to find the particle at
X is equal to SAR of
x Time s of
X I really haven't done anything that we
haven't done
before now in quantum mechanics like in
any other sensible statistical Theory
the sum of all probabilities should add
up to
one so the sum of s star s should add up
to one but when probabilities refer to a
continuous
variable we don't talk about the
probability that the particle is located
exactly at point
x that's too sharp the probability that
a thing is located exactly at any given
X is zero we talk about the probability
that it's located within a range of X or
better yet we talk about the density of
probability we talk about the
probability
density and we integrate this over a
little range of x to find the
probability that you're in that range of
X we do something like that here if we
want want to know not whether the system
is definitely specified at a but we want
to know whether it's in a range of a we
we sum over them but uh here we sort of
have to do
it total probability equal to one that's
the condition that the integral of SAR
of
x s of X DX is equal to one total
probability of the system has to add up
to one
and the only as I said the only new
thing here is that we have to replace
sums by integrals and that does make
mathematical subtlety that we have to
worry
about
but it's sort of in the mathematical
details okay what about the inner
product between two State vectors one at
X and one at X
Prime well here we go back for
inspiration right back to uh
right back
to this
case Zero if a is not equal to a prime
and one if a is equal to a prime and
we're not going to be able to quite get
away with that here
we're not going to quite be able to get
away with the statement
that x x
Prime is equal to 0 or
1 we are going to say that if X is not
equal to X
Prime then it's
zero but we're not going to say that
when it's equal to X Prime that's it's
one that would not lead us anywhere
what we're going to say is that it's a
function which vanishes unless equals x
xal x Prime but has area one under it
we'll see how that works out we'll see
what that does for us in a
moment what it really comes down to is a
different normalization here but again
the basic idea that states are
orthogonal If X is not equal to X Prime
that we will retain but the numerical
value of what we get when X is equal to
X Prime we're going to take to be
slightly different and in fact we're
going to invent a function not we are
directed the direct Delta function x - x
Prime the direct Delta function is not a
real mathematical function although by
now I think mathematicians have defined
it uh to death so that it is a real
mathematical
entity uh but for our purposes we can
think of it in a very simple way it's a
function which is zero well let's say
let's take Delta of X not Delta of x - x
Prime this is basically Delta of x - 0 x
Prime Z the function Delta of X it's a
function which is zero unless X is equal
to zero that's the same as saying this
thing is zero un less as X is equal to X
Prime so if this is
X it's Z
everywhere except xal X Prime and at xal
X Prime it's a very high narrow
Spike how high and narrow high enough
and narrow enough that the area under it
is one
unit that means if it's approximated by
a narrow interval of size Epsilon that
it has height one over
Epsilon and then you imagine the limit
where you take Epsilon smaller and
smaller
one / Epsilon higher and higher always
keeping the area under it equal to one
that's the dir Delta function directa
Delta function zero everywhere is except
when xals X Prime infinite in some sense
when X is equal to X Prime but in such a
way that the area under it is equal to
one
okay all right now let's use this
to further elaborate on what the meaning
of s
X's I'm going to guess and then we're
going to check I'm going to guess that
the meaning of s of X is the following
that if I want to write a general State
Vector
Sor that I can think of it as a sum over
the basis vectors but not a sum an
integral of course an integral because
uh the basis vectors are
continuous
DX of some
coefficients some coefficients well
let's no let's write it this way
s is equal to an integral DX of some set
of
coefficients I'm going to guess what
they are I'm going to guess that the S
of
x
times the I times the
um the State the quantum state where the
particle is located at X but then we're
going to add them up for different X's
there's exactly the same thing that we
did for ordinary Quantum systems except
this was replaced by a
sum all right now I've given you two
distinct definitions of s of x one is
that it's the inner product of the state
Vector with the igen vector X I'll call
it the igen vector of X the other is
that it's the expansion coefficients in
writing S as a sum over
vectors now if you're a little bit
uncomfortable with the idea of a
continuous basis of vectors that you
integrate over you're in good company
the mathematics of this is
um as I said by now it is been made
rigorous but it's it's it it's um it
took pages and pages and pages and pages
and books and books and books on
something called distribution Theory to
make sense out of this with Precision
but it's pretty intuitive it's pretty
intuitive and we'll we'll stick with
that all right so let's calculate oh
let's put a prime here this is a sum an
integral it doesn't matter uh it doesn't
matter what you call the integration
variable let's call it X Prime and now
let's calculate the inner product of X
with
S as I said there were two different
definitions of s of X let's check that
they're the same so here we have it
integral d x
Prime s of X
Prime in a product of X with X
Prime what's the inner product of X with
X Prime I think I wrote it someplace
where is
it I think I erased it
that's equal to the in to the integral
DX Prime s of X
Prime Delta of x - x
Prime okay what is
that all right first of all Delta is a
function which is zero everywhere at
except that xal X X Prime so that means
that in doing this integral here you'll
only get a contribution when X Prime is
equal to
X that means the answer is going to come
out to be proportional to S of
X furthermore the area under this Delta
function is exactly
one if we imagine that this Delta
function is a pinched narrower and
narrower High Spike so that the area
under it is one then this integral would
tend to S of X the rule is if you have
an integral over a Delta function like
this it simply picks
out the value of the integration
variable where the Delta function
vanishes sorry where the argument of the
Delta function vanishes where x - x
Prime vanishes that's where the function
is not
zero and the integral of a function with
a Delta function just gives you the
value of the function at the point
x that's a rule we might as well write
that down let's write that down as a
rule integral Delta of x - x Prime f of
x Prime is always equal to F
ofx it picks out the value X Prime equal
to X that's a part of the definition of
the Delta
function okay so it's just equal to S of
X and we find
mind consistency that the thing that we
called s of X over here is the same as
the thing that we called s of X over
here all of this has its exact parallel
for the uh for the ordinary
systems bottom top integral on bot
bottom board yeah so I'm looking at s of
X Prime
Times the C the C Vector X and adding
them up superposing I'm trying to figure
out where are the which are the uh which
are the basis vectors these are the
basis vectors all right let's let's
compare that
with s is equal the sum over a a prime
let's call it a
prime s of a
prime a
prime
okay if we use the fact that a and a
prime are orthogonal and do exactly the
same thing except replacing sums by
integrals
we will also find that uh that that the
s that appears here is the same as the
inner product of s with the basis
vectors so I've really done nothing that
we haven't done before I appreciate it's
a little possibly a little
unfamiliar uh but all it
is is same thing we've done
before so so the the S of X Prime sort
of plays the same role as the Alas and
some other the X Prime plays the same
role as the a prime here yeah the S
plays the same role as the S the sum is
replaced by the integral sum over a
prime is replaced by integral the X
Prime and otherwise it's exactly the
same now let's calculate the inner
product one quick
question it may be nitpicking or
something but on the left hand side
where you have
the draax formula lower right hand
corner yeah you've got a vertical line
between the
AIS over here in the middle
formula there's no vertical line thank
you okay good cuz it could have been a
line or I got you got you got you right
nope absolutely
how about the inner product of two
vectors well the inner product of two
vectors is some inner product but one
way of calculating the inner product
let's go back to ordinary uh to ordinary
quantum mechanics ordinary means for the
uh discrete systems here we don't need
this right
now how do we calculate the inner
product let's take the let's take it all
right inner product of s with
Fi we first write s and fi as sums over
the Bas basis vectors so this is equal
to sum over two sets of basis vectors A
Prime and
a s star of a prime time a
prime that's the bra Vector we complex
conjugate of course when we deal with
bra vectors that's the S half of
it and then the F half of it is the sum
of a
a of f of a
time
a five of a being the coefficients of
the F Vector s star being the
coefficients of the S um bra
Vector all right now the F of a is just
a number SAR of a is just a number and
the inner product of a prime with a is
just the chronica Delta so all of this
adds up to sum
of SAR of a prime
F of
a and then a chronica Delta of a and a
prime which is exactly the instruction
to set a equal to a prime now I think
you've seen that before this is simply
the rule about row vectors if SAR of a
is represented by a row Vector SAR of A1
blah blah blah blah blah and F is
represented by a column Vector then this
is is just the rule to take this times
this plus this time this plus this time
this plus this times
that so this is the common Garden
variety quantum mechanical in a
product I'm not going
to we don't need to go through the same
exercise here we can immediately write
down what the result is going to be just
by
analogy it's almost not even an analogy
it's just replacing wherever we see A's
put X's and wherever we see some putut
integral the inner product
of two State
vectors for a particle on a
line is
integral
DX SAR of
x f of
x it satisfies incidentally one of the
basic rules of inner
products what happens to an inner
product if you interchange the two
vectors what's the relation between the
inner product SFI and the inner product
F
SI complex conjugation now what would
happen in here if you interchange s with
Fi you'd wind up writing F star here and
S here that again would be the inpr uh
the complex conjugate
and for exactly the same reasons all
right so this is equal to
this for both discrete systems and for
these continuous
systems inner products the inner product
of a vector with
itself is the norm of the
vector and just as in previous examples
you normalize the vector to one to
Express the fact that total probability
adds up to
one
so not much difference just a difference
of um of
notation and
um what's I think what gets to be
confusing about it is you know both of
these things you know about these simple
row vectors and column vectors and you
know about functions but you're not used
to thinking of fun functions as vectors
or maybe you are if you are good but if
you're not used to using F thinking of
functions as vectors F of XS or function
s of x's then you have to get used to it
but it's not but functions are vectors
in a vector space you can add them you
can multiply them by complex
constants uh and you can add them you
can um multiply them by numbers and so
they satisfy the axioms of a vector
space space of function f is a vector
space now sometimes you may want yeah in
more classical mathematics would would
you put as the limits of integration
minus and plus infinity you
would which incidentally says
something it says that we shouldn't be
thinking about
functions which grow at Infinity for
example right we should be only thinking
about functions which are square
integrable now we're going to have to
we're going to have to modify that
square integraal means you square them
this is called squaring them that the
integral exists functions which grow at
Infinity won't do that now those are
crazy because so would say that all of
the if you had functions which grew at
Infinity where would the probability be
the probability would be all located uh
off at infinity and that's not what we
want we want to be talking about
probability distributions which a total
finite probability under
them
so uh that
means we should take perhaps with a
grain of salt the idea that we can write
down any function but for the moment
we're we're going to be a little bit
loose about
that
okay I I think I'll slow down here for a
few minutes and let you digest that and
ask uh for questions
yeah no no no no no
I yeah go ahead no I I I didn't want I I
meant about this but okay maybe this is
quick it seems like just about
everything must be entangled with
something almost all the time is that oh
yeah yeah yeah you're entangled with all
sorts of things in the environment and
we haven't talked about the importance
of a complex environment
uh it's not so important in the very
foundations of the subject but it is
important to why we see the world the
way we are that we're constantly being
bombarded and getting getting entangled
with
things um has a theory of distribution's
been useful for physicist or is it just
oh boy certainly well okay so so it's
not just some U it didn't just clean up
the the direct Delta function issue Oh
you mean has well oh that I I see what
you mean mean you mean has it done
anything else besides clean up the I
don't know I don't know I don't know I
think it's made rigorous a set of
Concepts that physicists use all the
time
uh has it uh
really changed no no it um the theory of
distributions yeah I'll tell you what
what it did for math for
physicists it uh
made them have to argue less with
mathematicians it was one of the many
examples where mathematicians got
dragged screaming and kicking by
physicists uh of course the opposite
also happens but uh it was an example
where mathematicians at first looked at
this thing and said what are you crazy
that doesn't make any
sense it's non-rigorous and uh and in
time they came to peace with it through
defining it
in in their own way but no I I don't
think the mathematical structure of it
has influenced physics as much as you
might have
expected
uh unfortunately because there are big
problems of confusion related to it in
Quantum field Theory and it hasn't
resolved those problems
okay okay next place we want to go is
observables we want to talk about
observables and give some examples of
observables observables are linear
operators what are linear operators
acting on a space of functions they're
operations on the state on a function
that gives another function
if you have a linear operator let's call
it
m for some reason I've saved L to stand
for
observables and I've used previously M
for a general linear operator so let's
continue to do so whatever m is it's a
machine and thought of as an abstract
operator in a
space it takes a state Vector into
another state Vector S Prime let's say
or a vector in the vector space but it
it also can be thought of as a thing
which acts on Wave functions every state
has a wave function that describes
it and the um the machine oh that's why
that was why we called it m yes I
remember now we called it m for machine
the machine can also be thought of as
acting on a wave function to give
another wave
function so let's think of it that way
uh let's think of it in concrete
terms as an action that we do on a wave
function to produce another wave
function now it's
linear linear means that when it acts on
the sum of two functions it gives back
the sum of the results it means that if
it acts on a function which is a
numerical product a numerical multiple
of some function it gives back the same
numerical uh
multiple all the ideas of what a linear
operator
are continue to be exactly the
same let's talk about some linear op oh
oh okay that's that's the notion of a
linear operator now what about a Herm
Mission linear
operator I'll tell you the definition of
Herm Mission we we've talked about it
before but I'm going to give it to you
in a condensed form the condensed form
is also true for all of the vector
spaces we've studied and you may
recognize it uh if not go back and prove
that it follows from the previous
definitions a Herm Mission operator Herm
mission for operators is roughly
speaking the analog of
real as opposed to
complex okay here's what's true about
Herm Mission operators if you have a
Herm Mission operator which I will now
call
L then it has the property that if you
take if if you act on a wave function s
or state Vector s and take its inner
product with
Fi that that is equal
to s l f but not quite what do I have to
do with
it complex conjugated now if L were not
let's go back a step supposing ill was
not her Mission would this be right not
quite what we have to do
we'd have to put a dagger
here in other words we'd have to roughly
speaking complex conjugate
L okay if L is Herm
Mission then the rule for
that is that it's mate it's Matrix
elements it's in it's um when sandwiched
when sandwiched in opposite
order you don't have to complex
conjugate L because it's already the
analog of real
this is the condition that an operator
is Herm Mission that's important because
Herm Mission operators are the class of
observables okay so let's work out one
or two Herm Mission operators while
we're at
it uh I guess we'll need we may need
this
so let's work out a
couple first of all one of the simplest
things that I can do to a wave
function I don't know what's they there
are many simple things I can do to
it but a very simple thing is to
multiply it by
X an even simpler thing would be to
multiply it by a simple
number but let's take slightly more
complicated multiply it by X multiplying
by X gives back a function so this is at
minimum an operation on a function is it
linear sure it is if x multiplies s of X
let's say plus 5 ofx
it gives x s of X Plus x f of
x in other words when it acts on a sum
it gives the sum of the
results if it acts on a numerical
multiple of a s it gives back the the
numerical multiple so it's a linear
operator question is it her
mission is it a Herm Mission operator
okay so let's check here's what we have
to take we have to take
s in a
product
of
X Time
5 that's this one oh sorry I think I I
think I wanted to do it the other way FX
SI the top
FX
s and ask whether this is true or not
we'll check in a minute
no X is not a number X is a function X
we've multiplied one function by another
function that takes functions to
functions X is not a number it's a
variable any given value of it is a
number but it's a machine that takes the
function s of X and replaces it by x s
of X all right so let's calculate the
wave
function of the uh K Vector is x s of
X the wave function of the bra Vector is
f star of
X the inner product
is let's put some brackets around it
bracket this is a c Vector inside the
Red Bracket and this is a bra vector and
the rule for taking the inner product
whoops I think I interchange star and
not star but the rule for taking the
inner product
is to
integrate so let's get rid of the
bracket here and just integrate the
X oops sorry
DX all right that's in this order what
about this
order this order over here the inner
product without the star without the
star the thing we're going to compare it
with is the same
thing except with siar
X
5x well look at it is this integral the
complex conjugate of
this yes it is a complex conjugate of f
star is f the complex conjugate of s is
s star and what about
x x is its own complex
conjugate so yes
indeed X is an operator which satisfies
the basic rule of permission an
operator that if you interchange the S
and the FI it complex
conjugates all right if
yeah what observable does X correspond
to position it is the
position is the Delta function
a igen vector of position well maybe
we'll come to that next time I think I
won't yes it is but uh but we'll come
back to that X is an observable what
does it correspond to it corresponds to
position of a particle we will prove
that by showing that the igen
vectors X that the vectors X are igen
vectors of that operator but not right
now we'll do that the next time it's
easy it's trivial a stupid question so
am I correct in assuming that when you
write X up there it's implied that that
is really F ofx the x is a function of
x x is an an F ofx yes it's implied that
that X is a function of
X it has a whole bunch that's right it
itself is a function which is
multiplying another
function all right so it's an operation
on a function which gives another
function
yeah that's exactly
right let's take another operation or
operation at
differentiation if I differentiate a
function I get a function that's the
first test of whether it's an operator
if I differentiate the sum of two
functions I get the sum of derivatives
if I differentiate a numerical multiple
of a function I get the numerical
multiple of a derivative it's a linear
function is it a Herm Mission operator
so here we have to here we have to get
ourselves a fresh
Blackboard and check once and for all
whether it's well check whether it's her
Mission
okay what happen what is let's call the
derivative
operation let's call it capital
d d on
S gives us some S
Prime what about wave
functions D when it acts on S of X by
definition now this is the definition of
how D acts it simply gives the S by the
X I may sometimes lapse into calling
this partial derivative with respect to
X that's fine doesn't matter there's
only one
X so it just
differentiates it creates a new
function it's a linear operator is it
Herm Mission okay so let's write down
the two two sides of the Herm Mission
condition here and see if they're the
same that's all that's all there is to
it the left side is
integral F star of
x times the
operation D on S which is just d s by
DX what's the other way of doing it or
the right hand side the other way of
doing it is integral
SAR not not doing the same thing doing
something different s star of x d by
DX and the question is whether this is
the complex conjugate of this so let's
write equals with a question mark we
don't know complex
conjugate so let's let's do this
integral over here
first of all the thing in the bracket
here is just equal to
integral s of
x d f Star by
DX just complex conjugate the complex
conjugate of a product is just the
product of complex conjugates so the
thing in the bracket is s of x d f Star
by DX and we're ask asking whether this
is equal to
this they look similar this has a s this
has a s this has a f star this has a
five star but unfortunately this one has
s differentiated and this one has s you
know what I mean SII and
fi how do you go from this to
this integration by
parts and integrate like this assuming
what are we assuming when we say we can
integrate by
Parts we're assuming that far away the
integral the uh the functions go to
zero that the endpoint contributions
from integration by parts don't give us
anything well of course the functions
must go to zero far away because the
integral of the total thing must be one
so we can integrate by Parts everybody
know what integrating by Parts is if not
find out fast it's simply a rule I'll
tell you what the rule is you can shift
the derivative from one if you have a
product the X this is DX here if you
have a product s of x times a derivative
of f star of X then you can simply shift
the derivative from one function to the
other but it's at a cost a
cost a minus sign right good so this is
equal to minus
the
integral F star of
X DC by
DX whoops we're in bad
shape this is integral F star D DX this
is minus the integral of f star DC DX
they are not equal in fact worse than
that they're absolutely the opposite of
each
other opposite in the sense of the
negative of each other can we fix it
well no we can't fix this but we can
redefine an operator which is Herm
Mission the redefined operator which is
her mission is not derivative it is
minus I the minus sign doesn't matter
you can put I or minus i d by
DX okay so let's go through it again and
check whether now it's her Mission this
is the new thing that we're going to
call and we're going to give it a
different name I'm not going to call it
D because it's not derivative it's minus
I * the derivative anybody have a good
suggestion for what I might call us P
brilliant
P
P4
momentum
momentum right and if I really wanted it
to be momentum with units of momentum
what else would I put there
where right or
left right well you can put on the left
but then you put better put it
downstairs all right but we're not going
to worry about har
bar we're going to use our usual
Convention of ignoring har bar for the
moment p is minus i d by DX let's see
what
happens over here we have to replace
this by an i over
here minus I thank you minus
I what about this
one we've complex conjugated
everything we better change the sign
because the complex conjugate of minus I
is plus
I and
so let's let's let's do it this way
minus
I and we should get plus I here if it's
her mission
why because in the process of taking the
complex conjugate every I gets converted
to a minus I and every minus I gets
converted to a plus I is it true
now yeah why because this is equal to
minus this that's what we proved over
here okay so if we stick an I here
because I changes sign on the complex
conjugate this little operation here
tells us that minus i d by DX is a Herm
Mission
operator it's a little odd isn't it that
minus i d by DX should somehow be a real
thing should represent a real thing and
that d by DX should not
but let's uh let's check something out
let's check something out right
now let's just uh we're going to finish
up in a
moment uh we haven't talked about
expectation values yet tonight but I
think you can guess how to think about
them expectation values in the state s
of an observable L are just the sandwich
composed of SII on both sides and L in
the middle so let's take the expectation
value of momentum it's integral SAR of
x s of x
X and then according to the rule here p
is minus i d by
DX is this real or
imaginary you're wrong it's real so
let's prove that it's real I hope it's
real God I hope it's
real okay all right so let's integrate
by parts
all right this is equal first of all
let's take out the minus I minus I
integral s
star of X DCI by
DX now let's integrate that by
Parts this is equal
to minus
I and then we can switch the
derivative we can switch the derivative
to the starred
variable integral
the S
Star by DX Time s of
X but then in doing the integration by
parts we have to change the
sign so here we have a little theorem
the integral of this thing here with a
minus
I is the integral of this thing here
with a plus I
what's the complex conjugate of this
whole thing the complex
conjugated you replace S Star by S well
s is over here you replace the S by the
the S by the X by the S Star by the X
and you replace minus I by plus I this
over here is the complex conjugate of
this can everybody see that or shall I
explain it further let's put a minus I
out here and write that this is equal to
DCI by this is just gives us DCI by
DX minus I DCI by
DX this is clearly the complex the
integral are complex conjugates of each
other the S by DX is the is the complex
conjugate of this that one's a complex
conjugate of this and I and minus I are
complex conjugates of each
other so given that this is the complex
conjugate of this and they're equal to
each other what do you say about a thing
which is equal to its own complex
conjugate it's
real so we prove a rather startling
fact that the
integral of SAR of x
minus
I DCI by
DX is
real no yes I did yeah right and again
it's because when you integrate by Parts
you pick up an extra minus
sign so instead of this thing being
minus its complex conjugate it's plus
its complex
conjugate okay so what did we learn we
learned that this is a Herm Mission
operator
it's a Herm Mission operator and
therefore an observable in quantum
mechanics the next time we'll explore a
little more we'll discuss what this has
to do with Foria
transforms we'll discuss questions about
what the probability for finding the
particle at different locations are but
then we'll also talk about what the
probability for having different
momentum
are and then we'll move to the schinger
equation we'll move to the evolution of
the um of the wave function this after
all Now is really in the classic sense
of the word a wave
function and we'll think about how it
evolves with
time oh one other thing we we could do
it tonight I think I think we're
probably
uh at the point of diminishing returns
are you
exhausted we could do one more thing let
me do one more thing for
you let's calculate an interesting
quantity and why it's an interesting
quantity we'll come through in a moment
so let's take a quantity which seems
very dull but which is interesting and
calculate
it it's the commutator of X with
p take any wave function whatever it is
s of X anyone
and we're going to do two things with it
we're first going to multiply it by X
and then we're going to multiply it by
minus i d by or operate with minus i d
by
DX all right this can be called
PX operating on
S this is p this is x in the order first
X then
P then we're going to calculate at the
other way x p on S what is that let's on
the other half of the Blackboard over
here we're going to write
X Time - i d by
DX s of X and see what we
get in fact what we're going to do is
we're going to compute the commutator
which means we're going to calculate
this one with a plus sign I'm going to
calculate this one with a plus sign and
this one with a minus sign all right so
this one with a minus sign but before we
subtract them let's just calculate them
all
right this is just minus I and now the
derivative of a
product the derivative of a product this
derivative here now has to act on the
whole
result of X acting on S of x x acting on
S of X gives a new wave function and
then P acts on it so what do you get
when you hit
the product you get two terms the first
term is the derivative of x * s
derivative of x is just one so the first
term is just s of
X and the second term is plus x d SI by
thex everybody agree with
that okay the derivative hit X and left
s and then the derivative hit s and left
X
that's this side over here now what
about this side over here here the D by
DX doesn't act on X it just acts this
way it just acts on S of X and gives us
minus i d by
DX s of
x h x sorry xus
i x d Side by DX
now let's subtract them let's take this
one with minus and this one with plus
this corresponds to taking the
commutator of X with
P acting on S of X commutator of X with
p is another operator and it acts on S
of X what do we get when we
subtract uh let's see this one now has
to come with a plus sign since we're
subtracting since we're subtracting we
have to change sign here and this term
cancels uh
yeah this term
cancels goes away and all we're left
with is s of
X that's all we're left with this term
cancels and we're just left with what is
it i s of x i s
ofx all right so here's what we found
for any s of X whatever for any s of x
the commutator of X with P acting on S
of X just gives is it plus I I think
it's plus I S of
X
now if an operator acting on any wave
function gives another
Operator Let if the operator XP acting
on any wave function is the same as I
acting on that same wave function for
any a function whatever it
follows that this operator is equal to
this operator another way of saying it
is if
XP minus I put it all in a big
bracket when it hits any way function at
all gives
zero then it means that this is zero
there's only one operator which gives
zero when it acts on every state on
every
Vector okay there's no Vector which
escapes when this thing hits it right
the implication is that this thing is
zero there's only one operator which
annihilates which kills every vector and
it's a zero zero so XP minus or
commutator XP is equal to I
if I put back the H bars there would be
an H bar here yeah I
bar we've seen things like this before
you may have to go back to your
classical mechanics we've seen things
before like this we've seen Pome
brackets which had similar
relationships the Pome
bracket of X with
p is equal to
one earlier in this course we discussed
the part the potential relationship we
had reason to discuss why commutators it
had to do with Schrodinger's equation go
back but we discussed the relationship
that there might be a relationship
between commutators and plus own
brackets and in particular the relation
involved this IH
bar this is actually where dra began his
discussion of quantum mechanics he said
there must be something analogous to a
Pome bracket in quantum mechanics and
the only thing you could think of which
had the right algebraic structure it was
anti-symmetric it uh it had a certain
mathematical structure was the
commutator and he postulated that
commutators and Pome brackets were
related with each other through an IH
bar and then proceeded to go exactly
backwards from the way that we went
he said if this is the if this is the
plus own bracket then this must be the
commutator and so there must be an
operator P whose commutator with X is I
and he went back through the operation
and discovered that P was minus i d by
DX so he went in the opposite direction
we discovered P by just playing a game
said let's see how about this operated d
by DX what does it do what we found is
that it was was not her Mission we had
to multiply it by I to make it her
Mission we explored it a little bit
found out some interesting properties of
it but the most interesting property is
that its commutator is equal to
ihar which
uh suggests that it's connected with the
Pome bracket the classical Pome bracket
being uh being
one okay of course the upshot of it is
and of course we need to do a lot more
to um to convince ourselves that the
operator minus I by DX really behaves
like quantum mechanical momentum we
can't just say oh it looks like a looks
like a Pome bracket it must be the
quantum mechanical momentum we have to
show that wave packets move with
velocities that are governed by uh by
the by this that the thing be that it's
conserved that it has all the properties
of momentum but we will
be some connection between this abstract
operator um minus I derivative with
mass and what and what and the idea of
mass well we would like to show that in
some way that it
is uh that it's the mass times the
velocity so what we'll try what we'll
eventually show is that if you have a
wave packet in other words a s of X
which is a concentrated uh distribution
like this that that wave packet moves
along the
x-axis with a
velocity which is given by the
expectation value of this momentum
operator divided by the
mass that's what we would like to show
that the velocity with which this wave
packet propagates along the
axis that velocity you can call the
group velocity it's usually called the
group velocity the velocity that the
group of waves moves along times the
mass of the particle is equal to the
expectation value of the
momentum now once we do that then I
think we're uh we're and that it's
conserved that'll take us a long way to
calling it
momentum uh at some point we have to say
quantum mechanics is more fundamental In
classical
mechanics and the definition of momentum
should be through quantum mechanics and
then we should show it behaves in a
certain way when particles are heavy and
so forth
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu